Hello English learners,
welcome back to another
great lesson at English
Pod, my name is Marko.
And my name's Erica. And today
we're going to be building something.
That's right, we've got a
lesson about construction.
Cool, so we're going to be
working at a construction site today,
and we're going to learn a lot of cool
vocabulary with different types of tools.
And we'll also learn some phrases
that you can use to talk about work.
So even if you're not really interested in
building and making stuff with your hands,
you will learn some language
to talk about work in general.
All right, so before we get started
with this construction dialogue,
let's take a look at vocabulary preview.
Vocabulary preview. Well, Marko,
we're going to look at two words now.
And like you said, we're building
something in this lesson, right?
Right, we're going to be building a deck.
A deck. A deck.
All right, so a deck. What is that?
Basically, it's an elevated
wooden platform that
houses will have like in
their backyards maybe.
So it's a platform that's a little bit
higher off the ground, behind your house.
So it's very popular for
houses to have decks,
and people will put
out a table and chairs,
and maybe have lunch
out there or something.
Barbecue or something?
Yeah, okay, so a deck.
Now, they're building this deck
and they need to follow some plans.
Plans. Plans.
The plans that we're talking
about are construction plans.
Yeah, it's kind of like the map for
the deck, how you're going to build it.
Exactly, so we can have
floor plans, for example.
So that shows you how the building
looks, like where the different rooms are.
And like a house, right? So it's
basically the map for a construction.
Okay, great, so two
interesting words.
We're going to hear both
of these in the dialogue.
Now, why don't we get
started and find out what's
going to happen as
they're building this deck.
[Music]
All right, ladies and gentlemen,
we've been hired to build a deck on this
here house and turn this boring
and drab lawn into a backyard oasis.
There is one catch though.
We've only got one day to finish this.
So I'm going to need
everyone to give 110% today.
It's going to be tough, but
we've got a great team here
and I know that together
we can tackle this project.
That being said, let's get to work.
That's right. No, remember,
we've been over the plans, but
we really need to make sure
that everything is up to code.
The home inspectors
here are pretty thorough, so
please make sure you
follow the plans exactly.
And remember, the carpenters rule
of thumb, measure twice, cut once.
Okay, guys, let's get at it.
Bob, pass me that hammer.
[Music]
The nails won't go in. What is too hard?
I think I'm going to need the nail gun.
[Music]
That did it.
Hey, do me a favor and help
me cut this two by four, will ya?
Pass me that circle saw and
grab hold of the end of the board.
Now, how may I drill some holes
in it so we can place the bolts?
[Music]
I think you should sand the edges.
Look at all these splinters.
Someone could get hurt.
Jeez, you got to take pride in your work.
Yeah, you're right.
Pass me the sander
and I'll take care of it.
[Music]
Julia, get over here with that level
measuring tape and that box of screws.
Oh, no. Look out below.
[Music]
Alright, so there are a lot
of people building the deck.
They have to build it fast.
They've only got one day.
So it's a really big challenge, huh?
Yeah, and I think this is
a good lesson in maybe
not rushing through
important projects, right?
Exactly. So we saw some really
interesting tools that they were using.
So why don't we look at that
first in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
Alright, so we've got some
language all about tools.
So why don't we just get started?
So they mentioned a nail gun.
Nail gun.
A nail gun.
So we all know about
hammers and nails, right?
Right, so the nails are
what you put in the wood.
Exactly.
Now this is an advanced tool so
you don't have to use a hammer.
It's kind of hard to explain so why don't
we listen to the sound this tool makes?
[Music]
Well, I guess like its name suggests
it's a gun for putting nails in wood.
Yeah, it actually uses compressed air
to push nails really fast into the wood.
Alright, so there are nailing
some pieces of wood together,
but they also needed to cut the wood and
they said, "Help me cut the two by four.
" Yeah, she said, "Help
me cut this two by four.
" So a two by four.
This is a very popular type of
wood that you use in construction.
A two by four is basically
two inches by four inches.
So two inches high and four inches wide.
So it's the most popular and common type of
wood that you would use for construction.
A two by four.
You'll hear it all the time.
So they're going to cut the two by four.
And C said, "Pass
me the circular saw.
" A circular saw.
A circular saw.
So a saw we understand is
something you used to cut wood.
But you have many types of saws.
You have a band saw.
You have a circular saw.
And this one makes this sound.
[Music]
So I guess it's called a
circular saw because the
blade or the cutting
part is shaped in a circle.
Yeah, a circular saw.
So after they cut the piece
of wood, one of the guys said,
"I think you should
sand the edges.
" To sand something.
To sand something.
All right.
So if you want to sand usually
a piece of wood, you want
to use paper covered in
sand to make it very smooth.
Yeah, exactly.
And so they also mentioned a sander, right?
A sander is basically a
machine that has this sand
paper on it and will do
the hard work for you.
All right, so to sand
something and a sander.
Now our next word is
very related to sanding
some because if you don't sand a
piece of wood, it might have splinters.
Splinters.
So like I said, if you cut a
piece of wood, there are
little pieces of wood that
stick out and you can get hurt.
They can get under your skin.
Yeah, so tiny, tiny parts of wood.
That's called a splinter.
A splinter.
Okay, so why don't we
go up onto our next tool.
They were talking about a level.
A level.
The level.
All right, so this is a tool
that all carpenters have.
And it's basically a tool that
has a little bit of water in it, right?
Yeah, and it helps you make sure
that everything is straight and flat.
Exactly.
So that's a level every carpenter
has it and also a measuring tape.
A measuring tape.
Now I'm sure if this was a
video podcast, we could show
you what a measuring tape
was and you really understand it,
but we'll do our best
to describe it for you.
So a measuring tape is
like a ruler that rolls up.
Yeah, it's a very convenient
ruler because it can roll up and you
can measure something that is
maybe six feet or a three meters long.
And you can extend it and
when you're done measuring,
you can put it back and
just put it in your pocket.
Yeah, every carpenter has one.
A measuring tape.
All right, so that's our last tool
that we're going to talk about.
So why don't we move on
now to fluency, both where we've
got some phrases that you
can use to talk about work.
Fluency Builder.
So when the contractor
started giving the instructions,
he said, "I need everyone
to give 110% today."
To give 110%.
So when you give 110%, you
are basically trying very hard.
Yeah, you give everything
you have to your job.
Right, so it's not only 100%, it's
110, more than what's needed.
So no lunch break.
Exactly.
So as they were talking
about the instructions, one
of the guys said, the
carpenter's rule of thumb.
A rule of thumb.
So this is an interesting
phrase, rule of thumb.
What does that mean exactly?
Okay, well, you know what?
I think we can understand the meaning pretty
clearly if we listen to some examples.
Example one.
The rule of thumb in
making a sale is confidence.
Without confidence, you don't make a sale.
Example two.
The Taylor's rule of thumb
is twice the circumference
of the risk, is the
circumference of the net.
Example three.
You don't have to take everything I
say about marketing as a rule of thumb.
One of the guys noticed a few
problems, you know, the splinters.
And he said, you've got
to take pride in your work.
Okay, so to take pride in your work.
To take pride in your work.
Why did he say that to her?
What is he trying to tell her?
Well, because she made some
mistakes, she didn't do such a good job.
He's wanting her to work harder,
work better, work more carefully.
Okay, and so she can be proud of
her work and say this is a job well done.
So when you take pride in
your work, you work so well and
do such a good job that
you feel really happy about it.
All right, good.
So why don't we listen to this
dialogue again for the last time?
And then we'll come back
and talk about construction.
All right, ladies and gentlemen,
we've been hired to build a deck on this
year house and turn this boring
and drab lawn into a backyard oasis.
There is one catch though, we've
only got one day to finish this.
So I'm going to need
everyone to give 110% today.
It's going to be tough, but
we've got a great team here
and I know that together
we can tackle this project.
That being said, let's get to work.
That's right.
No, remember, we've been
over the plans, but we really
need to make sure that
everything is up to code.
The home inspectors
here are pretty thorough.
So please make sure you
follow the plans exactly.
And remember, the
carpenters are rule of thumb.
Measure twice.
Cut once.
Okay, guys.
Let's get at it.
Bob, pass me that hammer.
The nails won't go in.
What is too hard?
I think I'm going to need the nail gun.
That did it.
Hey, do me a favor and help
me cut this two by four, will ya?
Pass me that circle saw and
grab hold of the end of the board.
Now, how do we drill some holes
in it so we can place the bolts?
I think you should sand the edges.
Look at all these splinters.
Someone could get hurt.
Jeez, you got to take pride in your work.
Yeah, you're right.
Pass me the sander
and I'll take care of it.
Julia, get over here with that level
measuring tape and that box of screws.
Oh no, look out below.
So an interesting aspect of North
American culture is a project like this,
building a deck or maybe
adding a room to your house.
Yeah, that's right.
And we call this DIY.
Right, DIY, do it yourself.
Mm-hmm.
So it's a very popular
summer project, right?
Right, so if you live in a
neighborhood in North America,
you might see the dad of a
family outside, building something.
And all his friends come over and they drink
beer and build this big thing together.
Right, so it could be a tree
house, it could be a deck,
it could even maybe be adding
another room to the house.
Yeah, and it's actually so
popular that there are tons
of TV shows about how to
build stuff for your house.
And there are a lot of really
big stores where you can go and
find like all of this equipment
for building stuff for your house.
Right, so basically there
are these big stores where
you can get anything
from paint to wood to tools.
Huge amount of material
so you can do it yourself.
Mm-hmm, you can DIY.
All right, so that's all the time
we have for today, but let us know
what you think and tell us if you
are into doing handy work like this,
like maybe building a tree
house or building a deck.
That's right, you can come
to our website at englishpod.
com and tell us about it as well, you
can also leave your questions there.
All right, so we'll see you
guys there and until next time.
Thanks for listening and goodbye.